Guide to the Lincoln Collection, Broadsides 1854-1922
University of Chicago Library
Lincoln Collection. Broadsides
1854-1922
6 linear feet (2 boxes)
Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
This collection is made up of broadsides compiled by William E. Barton. A pastor in Oak Park, Illinois, Baron published and lectured on Lincoln extensively. He also maintained connections with fellow Lincoln experts and carried out multiple research projects that delved into the many different facets of Lincoln’s life, times and family history. The Broadsides section of the William E. Barton Collection of Lincolniana contains materials relating to the social and political atmosphere of the Civil War period.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Rev. William Eleazar Barton (1861-1930) The Rev. William Eleazar Barton (1861-1930) was one of the early twentieth century's most prominent writers and lecturers on the life of Abraham Lincoln. Born in Sublette, Illinois, in the same year Lincoln assumed the presidency, Barton grew up in an environment heavily influenced by reverence for Lincoln. After pursuing undergraduate studies at Berea College in Kentucky, Barton earned his divinity degree from the Oberlin Theological Seminary in 1890. He served parishes in Tennessee, Ohio, and Massachusetts before becoming the pastor of the First Congregational Church of Oak Park, Illinois, a position he held until his retirement in 1924. Four years later, Barton accepted an appointment as lecturer at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee, where he also organized and served as pastor of the Collegeside Congregational Church.
Barton's work as a writer produced a number of denominational manuals for church organization and a series of books presenting the wisdom and parables of a character he named Safed the Sage. For the last ten years of his life, however, Barton was best known to the public as a prolific author and lecturer on Abraham Lincoln. His publications about Lincoln included The Soul of Abraham Lincoln (1920), The Paternity of Abraham Lincoln (1920), The Life of Abraham Lincoln (1925), The Great and Good Man (1927), The Women Lincoln Loved (1927), and The Lincoln of the Biographers (1930).
In the course of compiling material for his writings and talks, Barton visited Lincoln sites in Kentucky, Indiana, and Illinois; interviewed surviving Lincoln relatives and acquaintances; and traveled as far as California and England to collect information and conduct genealogical research on the ancestry of the Lincoln family. While acquiring a large collection of books, periodicals, pamphlets, manuscripts, and ephemera related to Lincoln and the Civil War era, Barton also purchased privately or at auction historical materials amassed by other Lincoln collectors such as John E. Burton and Osborn H. Oldroyd.
Scope Note
This collection is made up of broadsides compiled by William E. Barton. A pastor in Oak Park, Illinois, Baron published and lectured on Lincoln extensively. He also maintained connections with fellow Lincoln experts and carried out multiple research projects that delved into the many different facets of Lincoln’s life, times and family history.
The materials housed in this collection are political and propaganda broadsides from the mid nineteenth century. This collection is organized into two series: Series I: Broadsides and Series II: Oversized. This collection has been organized in consideration of the size of materials and aimed to make the collection readily accessible to researchers. The first five subseries of Series I are mirrored in Series II.
Series I is arranged into six subseries. Subseries 1, Election of 1860, consists of broadsides from this election year. The majority of these materials serve as propaganda for the respective parties. Subseries 2, Pre-Civil War, contains circulated broadsides alluding to the social and political atmosphere of the pre-war period. Subseries 3, Civil War, contains documentation and proclamations made by statesmen and army generals which were circulated throughout the states. Subseries 4, Election of 1864, contains broadsides of the ballots and platforms of the two parties in this election. Subseries 5, Post Civil War, contains memorial materials such as posters, ribbons, and speeches commemorating Lincoln’s life and his martyrdom. Also housed under this subseries are materials associated with Lincoln’s death, for example, the playbill and advertisement of the performance at the Ford Theatre at which he was assassinated. Subseries 6, General, contains advertisements and leaves from texts associated with Lincoln’s life which were published after his death.
Series II contains oversized materials and is organized into five subseries that mirror the organization of Series I.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Subject Headings
Barton, William Eleazar, 1861-1930; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865;; Collectors and collecting -- United States;; United States – History – Civil War, 1861-1865
INVENTORY
- Series I: Broadsides
  This series contains political broadsides from the mid nineteenth century to the post Civil War period.
  - Subseries 1: Election of 1860
    - Print: A. Lincoln and H. Hamlin, "Free Territory for a Free People", and Democratic Ticket, For President: John C. Breckinridge of Kentucky, For Vice President: Joseph Lane of Oregon, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous fragments, "The Abraham Lincoln Log Cabin", Fragments of portrait with Mrs. Lincoln and Robert Todd Lincoln, three unknown fragmentary materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fragments from Chas. Magnus print, "Birds Eye View of Sixth St. Wharf, Washington, D.C.," undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Pre-Civil War
    - Call for a Northern Convention, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Broadsides: "The Campaign Acrostic of the Alphabet" and "Estate Sale: 101 Prime Negroes, by Alonzo White", 1854 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3: Civil War
    - Broadside: Who is Responsible for the War? Who Accountable for its Horrors and Desolations?, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Broadside: Is the War a Failure?, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Polyrama of the Rebellion, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Rebel Terms of Peace!", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Two Roads to Peace, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - By the President, Abraham Lincoln, A Proclamation closing certain ports, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Message from the President of the United States, Abraham Lincoln, recommending a vote of thanks from Congress for Captain Louis M. Goldsborough’s services and gallantry displayed in the attack of Roanoke Island; and excerpt from book on soldier voting laws in Rhode Island, Connecticut, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Delaware, and Ohio, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The President to Gen. McClellen, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Proclamation by Brig. Gen. W.H. Emory, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - An Address to the People of the Free States by the President of the Southern Confederacy, Jefferson Davis, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Memorandum No. 57, Paymaster General's Office, concurrence of the Attorney General with Treasury office that African American soldiers are to be treated as freemen in all cases, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Circular. Headquarters, Department of the Gulf, Office of the Sequestrations Commission, 1863; Circulars from Headquarters by Maj. Gen. George B. McClellan: Army of the Potomac, Camp near Harrison's Landing, Va., 1862; Army of the Potomac, Fairfax Court House, Va., 1862; Circular from Headquarters by Maj. Gen. Comm. N.P. Banks, Department of the Gulf, New Orleans, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Army Relief Bazaar Buildings, Academy Park, Albany, N.Y., 1864 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 4: Election of 1864
    - President Lincoln and General Grant on Peace and War, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Platforms, Baltimore and Chicago, 1864; The Real Chicago Platform, As Expounded by the Democratic Orators at Chicago, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Ohio Union Presidential Ticket, (written in German), 1864; National Union Ticket for President, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Subseries 5: Post Civil War
    - Died, near the south-side rail road, The Southern Confederacy, satire on South’s defeat, (two copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Playbill and broadsides from the night Lincoln was assassinated: The Shuber-Garrick Playbill, "She Walked in Her Sleep"; broadside, President and Mrs. Lincoln attend Theatrical Performance -- for the last time; photograph of broadside, Ford’s Theatre, This evening the Performance will be Honored with the presence of President Lincoln, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Nation Morning Lincoln death: General Orders No. 3, Headquarters District of Alexandria, and 9th Army Corp. and General Orders No. 14, Headquarters Northern Division of Louisiana, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Proclamation by the Governor, Algernon S. Paddock, (Mourning Lincoln’s death); Treasury Department Notification, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Funerary Memoranda: To the Memory of Abraham Lincoln; In Memory of Abraham Lincoln; The Home Tomb of President Lincoln, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Order of service bulletins: Funeral Service in the City Hall, Portland; Memorial Services, City of Boston; Burial of Abraham Lincoln, Town Hall, Foxboro, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Obsequies of President Lincoln, order of funeral procession, (two copies); Headquarters Department of the East: Funeral services of Abraham Lincoln, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Funeral commemoration ribbons of Abraham Lincoln: "We Mourn, A Father Slain", "The Late Lamented President Lincoln", "The Martyr President", undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Emancipation Proclamation ribbon, post Lincoln assassination in support of the Emancipation Proclamation, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Stamps, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Lincoln monument: Certification of Mary E. Sterner’s contribution and membership of The Lincoln Monument Association, 1865; "National Lincoln Monument, Springfield, Illinois", 1869; 67th Congress, 2nd Session: H.J. Res. 127, Joint Resolution to erect the statue of Abraham Lincoln upon its original site, and S. Res. 291, Resolution accepting the invitation to attend the ceremonies at the dedication of the Lincoln Memorial, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Fremont Ticket, (four copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - By the President of the United States of America, Andrew Johnson; A Proclamation removing all restrictions on trade, by admitting articles hitherto declared contraband of war, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Journal, Extra, The Atlantic Telegraph, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - U.S. Senate, Impeachment of the President, ticket, (three copies), 1868 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Subseries 6: General
    - Book description and press critique of "The Great National Work, Lincoln Slavery". The History of Abraham Lincoln and the Overthrow of Slavery; Theatre Ticket, Madison Square Theatre: Walt Whitman on Abraham Lincoln, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "The Original Lincoln Log Cabin" and "The Bibliographer", undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series II: Oversize
  This series contains oversized political broadsides from the mid nineteenth century to the post Civil War period.
  - Subseries 1: Election of 1860
    - Kentucky Campaign -- Extra. Great Combined Circus and Menagerie, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Roll of the Republican National Convention, May 16, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Pre-Civil War
    - Broadside: "Some Account of some of the bloody deeds of General Jackson," undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Supplement to the Weekly Illinois State Journal, containing an address from President Buchanan, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Charles Magnus, "Narrative of Kilpatrick’s Cavalry Expedition," 1864 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3: Civil War
    - "True Democracy!: Eloquent Extracts," 1863; A Call to Arms, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - To Working Men, (two copies), 1864 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Epitaph. Here lie the mutilated and disjointed remains of the noblest form of government," undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Union Broadside No. 2: What the Copperheads and their Southern Friends Say," undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "A Traitor’s Peace (The Degrading Compromise): That the Northern Copperhead Leaders would force upon the country" (multiple copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Lyric sheet for Obadiah Wheelock's "Our Country Redeemed!" 1865 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Playbill for "The Libby Prison Minstrels," 1863 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Battles during the Great American Rebellion, 1861-1862 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Magnus’ Historical War Map: One Hundred and Fifty Miles Around Richmond," undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "What the Administration has done: Map Showing Progress of the, National Armies," undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Copies of the Emancipation Proclamation (negative photostats), 1863; The Original Manuscript of President Lincoln's Proclamation, of July 25, 1862, undated; By the President, Abraham Lincoln: Emancipation Proclamation, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Governor John Andrew: Governor of Massachusetts, A Proclamation," 1863 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "The Great Union Speech of Hon. Alexander Stephens," undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 4: Election of 1864
    - Broadside: "Elect Lincoln: Universal Anarchy, and Ultimate Ruin/Elect M’Clellan: In an Honorable, Permanent and Happy Peace", undated, Subseries 5: Post-Civil War (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - President Lincoln’s Farewell Address to His Neighbors: Springfield, Illinois, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Memorial announcement: To the Memory of Abraham Lincoln (reproduction), undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Memorial portraits of Lincoln: "Fallen, But Enshrined", "Tho’ Dead, He Liveth", "He Still Lives", "We Mourn Our Loved and Martyred Guide", "We Mourn Our Nation’s Loss", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Reward poster: $100,000 Reward! The Murderer of our late beloved President, Abraham Lincoln, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "The Cost of a Rebel Peace", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Democrats Rally!" undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Announcement Poster: "Fremont Meeting", 1856 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "The Great Impeachment Trial of President Johnson: The Only Full and Impartial Report," undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Announcement: Odd-Fellow Hall, J.H. Surratt lecture, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Salt River News Extra, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Headquarters Delegations from 1st, 2nd, 3rd. 4th, 5th, 6th and 7th Senatorial Districts," authored by Stephen A. Douglas, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 30)